[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is, eh... Samyutta Nikaya 45.1.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's called Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: It starts by the Buddha saying, bhikkhus, ignorance is the forerunner in the entry upon unwholesome states with shamelessness and fearlessness of wrongdoing following along.
[SPEAKER_02]: For an unwise person immersed in ignorance, wrong views springs up
[SPEAKER_02]: For when a wrong view, wrong intention springs up.
[SPEAKER_02]: For when a wrong intention, wrong speech springs up.
[SPEAKER_02]: For when a wrong speech, wrong action springs up.
[SPEAKER_02]: For when a wrong action, wrong livelihood springs up.
[SPEAKER_02]: For when a wrong livelihood, wrong effort springs up.
[SPEAKER_02]: For when a wrong effort, wrong recollection springs up.
[SPEAKER_02]: For when a wrong recollection, wrong composure springs up.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the opposite applies for knowledge, when a person has knowledge instead of having ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, there's another sutta, Samyutta Nikaya 56.17, that mentions what is that ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it says, a monk asked the Buddha, Venerable Sir, it is said, ignorance, ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is ignorance, Venerable Sir?
[SPEAKER_02]: And in what way is one immersed in ignorance?
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha says, bhikkhu, not knowing suffering, not knowing the origin of suffering, not knowing the cessation of suffering, not knowing the way leading to the cessation of suffering, this is called ignorance, bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it is in this way that one is immersed in ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the opposite.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the true knowledge that would give rise, as the sutta I read before says, that would give rise to the factors of the Noble Eightfold Path?
[SPEAKER_02]: It says, knowledge of the origin of suffering, knowledge of the cessation of suffering, knowledge of the way leading to the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is called true knowledge, bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it is in this way that one has arrived at true knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: We were mainly thinking of focusing on the aspect of right speech and the reason that sutta is important is because it's clearly saying that
[SPEAKER_02]: Wrong speech happens because of wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: It arises because of wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And wrong view is there because of ignorance, because of not understanding the Four Noble Truths, because of not being Noble Disciples.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's often the case that people would think that right speech is just about adopting certain
[SPEAKER_02]: external mannerisms and ways of, like we were discussing, non-violent communication and patterns of expression, in that superficial sense, thinking that that in and of itself constitutes wrong speech, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: Right speech, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, right speech, and that you would avoid wrong speech just simply by adhering to that, which is essentially just a kind of a
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, I thought of bringing up, starting with this sutta, because then we can start to lay out how is it that simply on account of having wrong view, even if a person is trying to do their best to speak a certain way, they would still not be partaking in that right speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, white speech, fundamentally, is about communicating that which is wholesome or beneficial for oneself and for others as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that depends on having the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one can speak, let's say, politely or be considerate
[SPEAKER_01]: And not in any coarse sense be violent or speak harshly, swearing and all the rest of it, which is definitely better than not doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But right speech as a factor of the path involves knowing what that path is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it sounds obvious if you put it like that, but actually, it's very easy to to to overlook that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, like unwholesome speech, just for example, like divisive speech, is unwholesome, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Setting up one person or one group of people against another group of people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes it's also better to just not speak, which does mean that you need to restrain your speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if one
[SPEAKER_01]: does not see the value in restraint and, you know, you just speak whenever there is the pressure to blur something out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, regardless of what you say, it's already an wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we can go into that, like, like, like what are the factors, from the point of view of the right view, that makes speech wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because, as you just said, it would be... the main purpose of right speech would be communicating... it would be wholesome if it's communicating the right view, but to kind of play devil's advocate, you would see also, in the suttas, when the Buddha would have a conversation with anyone, he would say, in the beginning, he would have...
[SPEAKER_02]: The Pali word means amicable and pleasing, or amicable and charming conversation with people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, that part is not described in the Sutta, because it's essentially pointless.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you could argue, well, the Buddha was sometimes talking about things that were not explicitly
[SPEAKER_02]: The dhamma, from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, not like it was just entirely a dhamma machine that only spoke.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the thing there as well is that
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I guess the way we could phrase the question is, what is it that makes speech wrong?
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you are adopting the external non-violent communication and stuff, what is it that would taint your speech?
[SPEAKER_03]: If you would act out of certain pressures, you see, Buddha, he didn't use these polite forms of phrases or conventions out of certain pressure, internal pressure, because he felt uneasy or, I don't know, fearful, something like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that would determine, basically, whether speech is wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, one thing also, like, in the line of what Ajahn says, like, if one hopes to get something out of what he's saying, whether it's, like, pleasing someone in order to kind of get approved by him or get something later from him, or even, like, if someone, like, talks about the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's a good example, because as you just said, yes, fundamentally, if the speech is about the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's rightly spoken from a mind free from aversion, greed, aversion and delusion, it would be the best type of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: But a person could be speaking about the dhamma for all sorts of reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like monks could be speaking about the dhamma so as to inspire lay people, so as to get donations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that would be a kind of greed right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, one thing to point out, now that we're on in that area, is that
[SPEAKER_02]: If you read the formula in the suttas, it's always this sort of templates.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would explain, for example, right view as there's nothing... wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing given.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no mother, there's no father, as we discussed last time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, wrong view... wrong speech would be described as...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's malicious speech, lying, divisive speech, harsh speech, but fundamentally, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as with the right view, it's not that those are only... the only wrong views that there exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there are myriads of ways that you can have wrong views that are not explicitly described by that formula.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with the four sadhipatthānas, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: We would say this is right recollection.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then the Buddha would talk about other things that are also right recollection, but they're not mentioned in that formula.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the same applies for the wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that only if it's, you know, coarse, harsh speech, like insulting someone, it is wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that is underlain by greed, aversion, and delusion is wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it might be the most beautiful kind of a... Poetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Poetic, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And about dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Totally about dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if the person's mind is contaminated with those three things, that speech is wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if, like, he memorized the discourse from the Buddha, and he is giving it with a better intonation than the Buddha is, and with a more pleasing kind of verbalization and deliverance, it's still wrong, because of the mind state behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's... we did actually discuss that in that talk about what is wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the state of the mind behind anything that you do,
[SPEAKER_00]: That really determines whether that thing is wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: With the right view, most fundamentally, what it comes down to is seeing the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: As the siddhas would describe, the fundamental thing that a person, without which a person cannot get the right view, is seeing the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I guess we could discuss that later in more detail.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in this context, what it would mean is,
[SPEAKER_02]: Being able to see, really, what that greed, aversion, and delusion is in the first place, so that you know whether your speech is affected with it or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you don't see that, if you haven't seen the signs of the mind, because you haven't been virtuous, restrained, and lived in solitude for long enough, then you won't even see the background contamination of your speech, even though
[SPEAKER_02]: externally, everyone listening to you, because they also don't see, as the Buddha said, in order to know the mind of another person, you have to know your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they might be very inspired by your speech and think that, you know, you're you're a great calm and gentle person, but inside, you can have lots of... even if you don't have it right there, well, you can still be liable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, fundamentally, it's kind of circumstantial whether you are, at the moment, not falling for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the right view, you would knowingly avoid wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, with the wrong view, you might be externally
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing what you think right speech is, but behind that, you don't actually notice that there's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the right view is that certainty that you can't be falling into unwholesome
[SPEAKER_00]: And not know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, with the wrong view, it can actually happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will, most of the time, happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That even though you think all this speech, action, livelihood, everything is fine, behind it, there is all sorts of lurking, you know, unwholesome motivations there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Yeah, and the interesting thing is, like, like the sign of the mind that you just mentioned,
[SPEAKER_01]: That becomes clear when one dwells in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it follows that if one is truly concerned with gaining right speech, one has to basically start avoiding other people, physically, and start learning how to be
[SPEAKER_01]: alone in seclusion, in order to pick up that sign of the mind, to even know what right speech is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not developing right speech by surrounding yourself by a lot of other people and and and learning external skills and training yourself that way, because that is entirely overlooking the rightness
[SPEAKER_01]: The root of the rightness of that speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because when you, for example, just practice...
[SPEAKER_02]: I developed the skill of talking to people, by going out and training myself in non-violent communication and using the right expressions not to upset people's sensitivities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that might be good in a worldly sense, but
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that is revealing you those intentions that we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, as we said before, intention is not like, oh, I'm saying this so as to not hurt this person's feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the... that's just a rationalization.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the intention we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's intention is, as the suttas would say, intention of renunciation, intention of sensuality or renunciation, intention of aversion or non-aversion,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what intention is, not like this explanation that you come up with about why you're doing something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that sort of intention would only become apparent on account of, yeah, seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, if you have been restrained and
[SPEAKER_02]: virtuous and blood and seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, for a while, and then you start seeing these signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you go back to talk to people, you would actually notice, oh, wait, there's this mental state here, um, that I would, I, like, in the past, I might have had this, and I might have said, well, I'm saying this because I'm trying to help this person, or because
[SPEAKER_00]: No, there is this form of greed there, and that would only be recognized as a result of you undergoing that training, not by
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so this also applies to people, including monastics, living in community.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if all sorts of, let's say, interpersonal difficulties arise, then you can go and sit in a circle and talk about your feelings, quote-unquote, but it's very dubious whether that is going to go to the heart of the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact,
[SPEAKER_01]: The more time you spend in such meetings, the less time you have to drown seclusion and pick up the sign of the mind, which is the factor for the right view, as we just said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's even a discourse, which appears at least three times in different places in the Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the Buddha says, like, you know, what are the six factors for harmony in the community?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then it talks about like friendliness, like acts of friendliness by body, speech and mind, keeping the training rules for monastic, sharing what has been rightly earned to the point of the contents of your alms bowl.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it says, factor number six,
[SPEAKER_01]: He has the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said that one is like the the roof that holds... the roof of a bungalow that holds everything together.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the pinnacle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's precisely the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if people have then, let's say, these interpersonal difficulties, rather than assuming that by going into all that,
[SPEAKER_01]: And sorting it out, that that is going to take away once and for all those problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, it is by gaining the right view, that the pressure that one would otherwise feel that one acts out of, that undergoes
[SPEAKER_01]: A radical shift.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, it's again, it's very questionable whether people should come together and in a sort of, let's say, group quasi-psychotherapeutical context, that might, in a worldly sense, people might think that that's beneficial, but there's absolutely no indication in the discourses anywhere that talking about those things is beneficial.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and we actually discussed last time that there was a sutta where the Buddha gives the instructions to the new monks, and one of them is that they should speak little, not that they should be practicing, you know... Yeah, put limits on your speech, and then restrain your senses, and become a forest dweller, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: Go to monks who can show you what is right view, which is again the factor there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, whatever difficulties you might have with other people, rather than going into the content of that and trying to figure out how to then live harmoniously together, basically, you want to adopt the perspective at the right angle to all that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and the thing with...
[SPEAKER_02]: There's also this notion of like the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Good friends are the kalyāṇamitta, and they would also kind of carry an implication that it's just the people who are nice to you, that you have a nice kind of relationship with, in a kind of a superficial sense that makes you feel nice and wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But really, when the when the suttas would define what is kalyāṇamitta, the Buddha himself was defining,
[SPEAKER_00]: What that means, it would describe how he would be teaching the dhamma for the benefit of the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, you know, it's something that people have to train themselves in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like someone, you know, to lean your head on or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something that it needs to be someone who has the right view, who can point you to what is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that's why it's a good friend.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because of how they make you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, even the Buddha said,
[SPEAKER_00]: When a Brahmin went to ask him, is it that you always... that you would never say anything that would displease someone?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you claim to be, you know, the foremost compassionate being or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he said, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, it's like, he gave a simile, it's like when a baby swallows something and it's about to choke.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you know, a normal person, sensible person, would even, like, put their hands in their mouth and even take out blood if it's necessary to save their life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said it's the same thing when he needs to, you know, point out the flaws in people's views and stuff, which is what
[SPEAKER_00]: But he was doing most of the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, many people might not feel like that's a kalyāṇamitta, a good friend, because it's not really making you feel very good most of the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even to Ānanda, his own disciple,
[SPEAKER_00]: His attendant, there was a case where he was... many monks, actually, were gathering together for the for the robe season festival, and they were gathering in these tents and stuff, and then the Buddha came and asked, like, why is it... why is it that there seem to be so many monks hanging around here?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, I mean, it was supposedly for a good reason, for sewing these robes and stuff, but the Buddha said,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he basically admonished all of them for not living in solitude, for delighting in company.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to Ānanda, his own attendant, he said, like, I won't treat you like a potter would treat his valuable pots.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, I will smash you and then the core is what will remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: The core that
[SPEAKER_00]: A good friend is the friend who will stage an intervention for you, not the friend who's giving you free drugs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is not...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's basically not who seems like a good friend.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and this kind of non-violent communication that you point out, like, not hurting people's feelings, like, kind of imply the fact that, oh, people, other people can impact my feeling, and I can impact their feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there is kind of this implication of...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm responsible for them, and you are responsible for me, and then we try to kind of flow together like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of a bit... Yeah, each person, like, that's already overlooking the responsibility that each person has for suffering in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Each person, it doesn't matter how much you insult someone, obviously it doesn't mean you should do it, but if a person suffers, that's because they haven't understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, by trying to create these safe spaces and trying to think that that's what creating a good community is about, like just avoid offending people at all costs, you are kind of implying that all suffering is out there in the things that other people do to you and not internally in your own views, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And another thing is
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's important to point out that, as well, that it's not bad in itself to try to be gentle and be polite, because that's a... that leads to more fluent interaction between people, actually, in the mundane sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is not that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is when you prioritize this, and then, because you automatically forget that there is something more important,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is, like, right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the Buddha would be, as you would say, he would use gentle speech at the right time, and he would know the right time for using not so gentle speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he has a more fundamental criteria than just how am I making people feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why sometimes he would be calling monks inept man and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that was the right thing to do at that time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I think he did that only with monks, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people who had already subscribed to the training and basically accepted him as their guidance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, well, actually, he also, when there were these other ascetics of other sects, we'll also use the same term,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, the point is, like, you wouldn't... if you prioritize just that superficial aspect, you will become complacent in thinking that on account of this, yeah, you are factually avoiding, like, some chunk of the amount of unwholesome stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you would be overlooking that there's way more work to be done
[SPEAKER_00]: on the level of those background intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that people stop there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, don't say that there's more work to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the further work is the meditation techniques and the focusing and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that I don't even then need to
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want to be questioning my intentions and look at that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just leave it there, leave the house half-painted, and then go somewhere else during the meditation session.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're not really cultivating the stuff that would make you... the type of meditation that would make you discern those unwholesome intentions when they're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was actually the Buddha's advice to his own son, Rahula.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's this whole discourse, which deals with speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says, like, you know, before you... What were the three?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, before you break out into speech, consider, is what I'm about to do wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, while you are talking... And so, this is the sati.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the mindfulness for the recollection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, while you are talking, keep your aim in mind, like, is this still wholesome?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very easy to start talking, because, you see, you might start talking with a wholesome intention, but you just lose yourself in your own speech, and while you're talking, it sort of deviates, and you end up almost doing the exact opposite of what you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to be on the ball while speaking, and then afterwards, perhaps when you are on your own in seclusion, you can still look back and consider, was that speech now actually wholesome or not?
[SPEAKER_02]: And see, the... that wouldn't be possible
[SPEAKER_02]: That what you just said, that the intention changes from unwholesome to unwholesome, if it were in the content of what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really the mind changes its inclination towards the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some form of greed that wasn't there arises, but you might be talking about the same topic, saying the same words that you might have otherwise said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing really changed on that on that level, but you internally now have a different impulse, a different
[SPEAKER_00]: There's something different that's pushing you now to say these same things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what makes it wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so... Yeah, you... it's always has to be recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: The... as the Buddha said, action is intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So anything unwholesome...
[SPEAKER_02]: cetanā is the word.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything unwholesome has to be that, not just like, you know, he didn't say action is the the movements you make with your hands and the sounds that come from your mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you purify that internal level by recognizing it first and foremost,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you wouldn't have to worry about what you say externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: You purify the source of the river in order for the, you know, later current to be clean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't, like, start from the ground up.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just wasted, wasting effort and you're never really going to get anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's essentially what's happening most of the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you would be... by trying to control your expressions and stuff, and thinking, okay, this is it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't look... you don't look any further.
[SPEAKER_02]: And... that's another thing with... the... like, when people have, for example, restless mental states, and worry, and a lot of...
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, hectic thoughts and stuff, they would think, well, I need to now use a concentration technique to calm myself down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But really, if you were actually restraining your speech rightly, first of all your actions, and then your speech,
[SPEAKER_00]: You would see... you refrain from all this useless talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha defined the ten topics that are not worthy of discussion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, talk about politics, food, sensuality, kings, clothes, money, relatives.
[SPEAKER_00]: gossip, it's called like talk of the well, like when people would go to a well and they would get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, street talk and talk of the well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you refrain from that stuff, then you won't have in the first place these
[SPEAKER_01]: So, rather than trying to solve the problem afterwards, when the mind is already spinning out of control, you are saying that you find yourself in such a state,
[SPEAKER_01]: One pillar there is the unrestrained speech on the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, instead of trying to clean something, then don't get it dirty in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of needing to clean after the fact.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you would see that then the purity
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it would become something that you no longer had to be hoping for or anticipating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, how people would say, well, today my meditation was not good.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's almost like, well, that's that's that's just something random.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it was a bad day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, purity is entirely in your hands.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you didn't do anything unwholesome, you can't be impure, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: If during the whole day you didn't engage in any unwholesome intentions, and right now you're not engaging in any unwholesome intentions, it's impossible to have a bad day in terms of your dhamma practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't mean it will be pleasant, but again... That's not the criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the criterion.
[SPEAKER_00]: The criterion is, am I giving in to aversion when there is displeasure?
[SPEAKER_02]: And that would give rise to a different kind of peace than the peace that comes when sometimes your meditation technique works.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a different...
[SPEAKER_01]: Earlier, you played devil's advocate for minutes and brought up the, let's say, friendly and amiable talk that the Buddha sometimes has, you know, when people come to see him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you should distinguish that from the gossip or the, let's say, idle talk, which is clearly unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it occurs to me that gossip in particular is a good example to reveal inauthenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, inauthenticity can be described as just uncritically taking over the views and the opinions and... or the opinions and the beliefs, rather.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without questioning whether they are true, you take them over and then you assume that they are just disconnected ideas latent in the back of your mind and that they do not affect how you act by body and by speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, furthermore, having those ideas already and seeing them as fairly harmless and innocent, you then pass them on to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that's what gossip does.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it has that similar structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You hear something,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't even can be bothered whether it's correct or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't see that you have a responsibility for what you accept and what you reject.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, on top of that, you pass it on to others, which is also within the sphere of your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to to fully reframe
[SPEAKER_01]: From just passing something on without being reasonably clear whether it's correct or not, that's already on the level of speech moving in in the direction of authenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, if you are more or less clear whether something is correct, it still doesn't necessarily mean that you should therefore pass it on to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you then break out into speech, so to speak,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that involves a whole other layer of considerations.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you said, like, yeah, what is unwholesome is to speak when there's pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that does imply the view that you can release the mental pressure by breaking out into speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, actually, there are two different domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if someone recognizes that you cannot
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, relieve that restlessness, or that worry, or that doubt, or any kind of mental agitation, by just talking about it, that... Or your emotions, like you said, like having this... talking about your feelings with other people, that releases it and makes you feel better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because I think it would be good to briefly clear that up, because
[SPEAKER_01]: I think the way that dhamma is presented nowadays has become so intertwined with a host of, let's say, more psychotherapeutical ideas, that the whole idea that to engage on that level and to just speak or learn how to speak about that, that that is somehow beneficial, I think needs a fair amount of qualification.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was just going to say, yesterday, Lana and I were talking about how it's like it almost feels like there's no kind of... like it almost feels like things could just kind of flow out, you know, like I'm not responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just was in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you need to see, like, that is a sign that there's development to be had, because you would see, okay, if there is that sense of connection, means
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not taking responsibility by default for what...
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be some sort of buffer, like, before you say things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that would be cultivated on account of the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you have been restrained beforehand, your mind inclines towards, as the Buddha would say, you incline the mind in different directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even way before you actually start falling into these traps, you would see yourself going that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it only ends up in that case where it feels like, whether it be by speech, body, body speech or mind, it only gets to this point where...
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like the unwholesome is almost like happening by itself, because beforehand, you were overlooking the little step-by-step progression towards that full-on...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a snowball, and then you don't stop it at the right time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just keeps going.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but that's connected to the other thing you were saying now, that the gossip and stuff, you wouldn't be able to tell
[SPEAKER_00]: If you had to determine what is wholesome and unwholesome by having some sort of list to analyze each topic...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so, this is about this and this, and it's 3 p.m. right now, and he... That's impossible to actually keep up.
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice needs to be to the point where
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even need to reflect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you already know before you even say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the dhamma should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's only when you take it on the level of that pressure, as you mentioned, that you would start to see it doesn't matter even...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't even need to worry about the content of what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be gossip if I'm not talking out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, any useless topics,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're like, by default, it won't even occur to you to talk about this, because you're not... that's that sort of stuff that truly serves no purpose, cannot come out unless you are feeling into pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you take that that as the standard, and then you ask yourself, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: If I don't say this right now, is my mind going to start complaining about me not saying?
[SPEAKER_00]: That pressure starts to build up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you can see, oh, if I speak, I'm actually kind of furthering the agitation of this wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you just keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you are surprised when you try to stop it and you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's because you've been letting it run wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where you... that's where the training is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And seeing that... when am I speaking out of pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you start to see the mouth as a kind of gateway that
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how much... like... like a dam that's holding water.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how big the pressure gets to let the water out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the one who has to actually open the dam and let it flow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't happen by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you were saying, like it's three different domains.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what you're thinking about and how much you want to say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't, if you succeed in not saying it, that's, that's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so... Yeah, but we should also now add that it, that we cannot fully go to the other side of the extreme and start determining to not say anything at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm saying, like, I don't mean not talking.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, when you see that there is the pressure, and then you refrain from that in that, like, with that background recognition, that's already a form of sati.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, it's good to bring that up, because the
[SPEAKER_00]: There's even the Buddha forbade this vow of silence, which is, ironically, the principle with which, like, I think, most meditation retreats operate, that you can't... you can't speak at all, or... or, like, just one or two words per day or something, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why that's wrong is because you're not even training yourself so that when you get out of there, you actually see what are the unwholesome intentions behind my speech that were making me stressed, agitated and lustful.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I wasn't in this retreat, you didn't learn anything about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but people will be able, like, when they hear this, I'm pretty sure they will be able to relate that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's, in a sense, it's much easier to just determine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not going to say anything for 10 days.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than leave that 10% window, where it's still okay to say something, because that now forces you to question, is it really necessary for me to say this?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actually much more unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and then that will force you to learn
[SPEAKER_00]: What is wholesome and what is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't be trying to wriggle out of the problem so easily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's factually, at some point, you will have to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that goes with everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: In general, the practices, the sorts of practices that people take on for running away from things and burying their head in the sand for a while, that's the kind of peace it gives you, but you haven't discerned why, when your head was out of the sand, why things were a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not really, well, you're not fixing the problem that the Buddha talked about, like that ignorance, not knowing suffering, not knowing the escape from suffering,
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of which, all of these wrong things come to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is... that can only be done by, as we've been saying so many times, the intention behind your action, being clear about it, and seeing that as a training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, day and night, you
[SPEAKER_00]: You are aware of whether your actions by, as you said in the Rahula Sutta, you would be reflecting, before I do it, is this really a pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: While I'm doing it, is this really a pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: After I did it, is it really a pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that is actually teaching you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, because you learn from your mistakes.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not taking this blind vow of silence, and then you look back and you reflect, oh wait, on that occasion, I have a feeling that that was that was not wholesome, and then you see why.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was it because of some external situation, or was it because at that moment I had this mental state of greed, aversion, delusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so that's what you recollect, the mental state.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will actually remember that mental state, because you know in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can look back and see what are the motivations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though it was a past event, you can see yourself, like, why you did something on that level that matters, that level of intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when it comes up again in the future, you have a reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, wait, this is the same thing that I did the other day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you start seeing it, again, in the mental internal level, where the
[SPEAKER_00]: The level of intention, on account of which, actual wrong speech can come to be.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that, like, oh, I did this, this is the same kind of situation as the other day, that doesn't even mean, like, it's the same from the outside.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it could be completely different.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: The image is just totally different.
[SPEAKER_04]: One, you're alone.
[SPEAKER_04]: One, you're surrounded by people.
[SPEAKER_04]: The actual content of what's happening is not... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it could be absolutely anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the things you say, for example, I was going to bring that up.
[SPEAKER_00]: The example of Mahākassapa, when he would be, you know, he called Ānanda, he called him a boy, and that, I mean, he's the Buddha's attendant, and that was, that sort of language would have been, or that sort of attitude would have probably been considered, like, how can an arahant say something like that to someone?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on the other occasion, like, when they were on the council,
[SPEAKER_00]: He forced Ānanda to confess a bunch of offenses, to see them as wrongdoings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, in general, he was just this kind of... like, he refused to... to shrug the monks, because he said, these days, monks are full of evil wishes, and they don't... they don't actually care about the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, he... that could be... by people who think the the the speech is about, as you said, the content of what you say, that could be considered as a as a form of wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because there would have not been any sort of predilection for greed, aversion, delusion behind him saying that, which only he could know, then... or another person, like, who also has the right view, then
[SPEAKER_00]: There wasn't any problem with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you don't take responsibility, and you think, oh, well, look, that monk speaks like that, so I can also do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you would think, you would still be putting it in the content, and you wouldn't be taking responsibility for seeing this mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: What state is it in right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, different people
[SPEAKER_02]: After you understand the way of suffering and stuff, you would have different... still different tendencies and ways of talking or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, some people might be more naturally, you know, meek and gently spoken, and other people might be a little bit
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, more abrasive.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that doesn't really mean anything fundamentally on the internal level, as long as
[SPEAKER_00]: There are obvious things that you cannot do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't go insulting people because...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that is what is defined literally as wrong speech in the in the formula that I just mentioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that is the obvious stuff that if you do it, you're automatically falling to wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, eh... another thing I thought was important to bring up, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also mentioned in the suttas many times that you shouldn't exalt yourself and put others down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think that is that's also included in the in the context of right speech sometimes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the thing with that is usually the assumption is...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, criticism is bad, essentially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you should be focusing on bringing people up,
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of putting them down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, like, it doesn't say... it says you refrain from exalting yourself and putting others down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't say you ensure that you put yourself down and exalt others.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because that would be a sort of self-denigration, which is also unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, or not even full-on self-denigration, like trying to almost artificially kind of focus on the good qualities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like someone's promoting wrong view, but you see, oh, you try to find like the positive aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So as to, you know, not put yourself up and
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sometimes with somebody's behavior you can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are about to do something unwholesome, you can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there are indeed other discourses where the Buddha even says how should one monk admonish another.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, but... And then it should be like beneficial, the timing should be right, with a mind of friendliness, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the whole idea that to not exalt oneself does not mean that one cannot, let's say,
[SPEAKER_00]: No, but I wasn't referring to, like, a person you're actually talking to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was referring to in the sense of views, like, when the Buddha, for example, said, you shouldn't be... he actually defined it in this
[SPEAKER_00]: Sutta in the Majjhima Nikaya, he said, how is it that a person falls into this denigration and self-exaltation, and how is it that they only speak dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is, like, people might think, again, that it's just by criticizing other views,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are somehow being considered arrogant that you need to kind of allow space for other people to be right as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is... the thing is... as the Buddha said, how do you... how do you avoid that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't avoid it by not point... by not pointing out that there is right and wrong, which is again kind of an easy way out of the situation and doesn't fix it at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's by
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of saying, talking in terms of me, like, I am wrong, you are wrong, I've refuted your argument, you're, you're... No, I see what you mean, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you, you instead say, whoever is practicing like this... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are attached to being.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the literal way the Buddha explained it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whoever has this sort of practice, they're attached to being.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't see the way out of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whoever practices this way, they have right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: They see the way out of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of saying,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, these people are arahants, and these people are total buddhismists.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't focus on the person, specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You focus on the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you criticize, and that's what the Buddha was doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was criticizing the views that people had.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like personally attacking people, and that's really... personally attacking or personally exalting himself, like to make himself feel, you know, make himself appear in that kind of personal sense, like there's some sort of contest between us and I'm trying to come out on top.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's really when you end up exalting yourself and denigrating others.
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you tell?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, a very practical sense, a practical test that you can do,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, if you are criticizing somebody's views, but then, do you feel like you actually now have a personal problem with that person as well?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you had to talk to meet that person whose views you're criticizing, would you have some sort of internal animosity or would you be able to treat them totally like a like a normal person on a kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the usual polite way that you would treat somebody else, or would you be like, that's that idiot that believes this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you would know if your speech is really rooted in... Yeah, and this goes back to the question of... to the discussion of patience that we had, like khanti, like the highest discipline or the highest austerity, but it's also paired with gentleness, often.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's the aim of ascetics.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to endure, still, somebody else's wrong view,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, are you going to challenge somebody?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if those views are actually wrong, are you going to challenge that because it's more pleasing for you to not have to suffer somebody else's wrong view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, is the dhamma just about stating what is the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you averse to the displeasure of seeing that someone has a wrong view and you're trying to call it out?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you will automatically end up debating on that personal level and the sutta describes actually that sort of a back and forth thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I am right, you are wrong, what you said before, what you said after, you said before, what you said before, you said after, I totally contradicted everything you say, go back, you're, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, try to rescue your t-shirt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Try to rescue your t-shirt if you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's a very... you see, that's not something that can happen by accident.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, just because you said, well, this sort of practice is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like a full-on you attacking somebody because you have a... you have... you are upset internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a very different thing because the Buddha spent all the time almost, like, half of the stuff he was saying was pointing at wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other half was
[SPEAKER_00]: Once that's done, then you know what's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't just decide that... you can't point out what's wrong because...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, he himself said, not pointing out non-dhamma as non-dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a form of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not recognizing non-dhamma as non-dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Refusing to recognize it so that you can keep that sense of superficial harmony.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Only if you have wrong view, would you be able to to engage in such a thing, because it's authenticity.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like bad faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is where the timing then becomes important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you might recognize a wrong view as wrong, but it does not necessarily mean that this is now the right time to address it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you need to take your own
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say mood or state of mind into account, but you also need to see whether the other person is to some extent receptive to what you are about to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might have to endure for quite a while somebody's wrong view and then find a proper occasion to say, look, actually, the whole thing is otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is
[SPEAKER_01]: A skill, but that only comes into play once you realize a wrong view as a wrong view, which is only possible when the view is right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and like you would... Like I just said, you're just meeting the person in a totally mundane sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not a discussion about dhamma, but you know that this person has wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't like, hey, by the way, yeah, that's that's not because that's not the right time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's, as I said, you need to know the right time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but in that time that you're not actually talking about it, if you see yourself being averse to the person on that personal level, then that's clearly a problem now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you still decide to point out the wrong view, even though, let's say, technically you're right,
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're doing it now, and you can't wait for the moment when you can finally just let it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what that desiccant reads.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see yourself then, you catch yourself, and that's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, that would always be on that internal level, not about what you're going to say to the person even.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.